Conference of Large City Boards of Education; Records apap083
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Conference of Large City Boards of Education Records
1968-1981
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Conference of Large City Boards of Education
apap083
1.0 cubic ft.
The Conference of Large City Boards of Education Records include some of the day-to-day operations of the Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education as documented through files kept by Eugene Samter, Executive Director of the Conference. The collection also includes Samter's testimony from the 1976 Levittown vs. Nyquist case argued before the New York State Supreme Court.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Jackelyn Freedman, Executive Director of the Conference of Large City Boards of Education in October 1989.
Organizational Sketch
The Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education was appointed as part of the Conference of Large City Boards of Education of New York State in 1978. Governor Hugh Carey appointed the Task Force to investigate school finance reform after the New York State Supreme Court ruled that the system of state school financing at the time was unconstitutional in the Levittown vs. Nyquist case.
Eugene Samter was the Executive Director of the Conference of Large City Boards of Education when the Task Force was appointed, compiling data, and publishing research in several reports. The materials in the collection are the files retained by Samter. The Conference of Large City Boards of Education is now known as the Conference of Big Five School Districts.
Scope and Contents
The materials in the Conference of Large City Boards of Education collection are from the files of the Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education kept by Eugene Samter, the Executive Director of the Conference. The collection includes correspondence, research materials and data, meeting information, and some interim reports and drafts of reports of the Special Task Force. Some reports and data are included with the correspondence. Topics covered include school vouchers, regionalism in education, the correlation between class size and student achievement, special needs students, and other issues related to education policy. Also included is Samter's testimony from the 1976 Levittown vs. Nyquist case argued before the New York State Supreme Court. The School Finance Reform folders include news clippings and research materials from school finance reform movements in New York, New Jersey, Ohio, and California, including the landmark Serrano vs. Priest case from California challenging how schools in the state were financed.
The collection is particularly strong in documenting research materials, but it does not cover the administration operation, and final report of the Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education closely.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized by folder. There are no series.
Education; Public schools--New York (State); Education--New York (State)--Finance; New York (State)--Education; Correspondence; Reports; Clippings; Carey, Hugh L.; Samter, Eugene; Conference of Large City Boards of Education; New York State Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education
- Correspondence, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 3)
- Research, 1979 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 4)
- Meetings, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 5)
- Meetings, 1980 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 6-7)
- Testimony of Eugene Samter, 1976 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 8)
- School Finance Reform, 1979 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 9)
- School Finance Reform, 1968-1979 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 10)
- School Finance Reform, 1971-1978 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 11)
- Second Interim Report, 1980 (Box 1 (Conference of Large City Boards of Education Recor), Folder 12-14)